USA,
Jersey City,
suburbs of New York,
September 21, 1948,
the man of steel,
American Tony Zell,
is now nothing more than a disjointed puppet in the Frenchman's fists,
Marcel Cerdan.
As the 12th round begins,
Tony Zell is not showing up.
Joy erupts in the French camp even before the referee's announcement.
The day after,
still in America,
First press conference of the new world champion in average points.
Playing to his advantage poses no problem for him.
Having to speak is another matter.
Fortunately,
Lucien Roub,
his bespectacled manager,
is here.
Who knows what he should say?
At the end.
No statement.
Before my fight,
I told you I would be thinking of you.
And now,
I am a world champion.
And really,
throughout that entire fight,
I was thinking of you.
I haven't stopped thinking about you.
And if I am world champion,
It's partly thanks to you too.
October 1, 1948,
when the Constellation from New York lands on the Orly runway,
Hundreds of them are already waiting for him.
Right away,
Cerdan begins his triumphant journey,
in the very car that Hitler had used during his visit to the capital.
Soon,
They number in the tens of thousands, gathered along the route.
We hadn't seen so many people in the streets for a sportsman since Julot-Ladoumègue.
13 years earlier.
Everyone wants to shake the champion's hands.
forgetting how fragile they are.
And of course,
despite the pain,
It is their time.
with his customary kindness.
How did this guy,
to the thin voice that now drifts under the porch of the town hall,
Was he able to captivate an entire country and become the first post-war French myth?
It's been 60 years since Marcel Serdant died.
And another,
still here
Marcel Junior.
He has 8 years of professional boxing experience behind him.
But above all, and always,
Like father, like son.
My father became a legend because he was a man who raised the French flag very high.
Here is a little Frenchman,
a few years after the end of the war,
part in the United States,
He meets the best Americans.
the best American boxers,
And he beats them.
Who hasn't listened to one of my dad's boxing matches at 3 a.m.?
4 a.m.?
For his world championship,
Everyone is listening.
He instilled pride in them by saying,
Yes,
The Americans came to defend.
But we,
French,
We went to beat them at their own place.
And he beat them on their own turf in America's most honored sport.
which is boxing.
Marcel Cerdan,
of Spanish origin,
born overseas in 1916,
in Algeria,
in Sidi Bel Abbès,
the city of the Legion.
Five years later,
his father was a butcher,
who likes business,
but that commerce doesn't like,
decides to try his luck in Morocco.
in Casablanca,
the white city,
which makes Lyoté and his family proud.
Even though the Cerdan family and their five children set up their shop in the Cuba district,
near the Arab city,
among the children with shaved heads.
Far from the business district and notable beaches,
Riviera all year round,
where a punching bag is already being used to promote the slenderness of these ladies.
Father Serdon also likes boxing,
especially when it pays off.
For the time being,
Marcel,
the younger brother,
He takes on a series of odd jobs.
Delivery person,
mechanic and above all,
apprentice footballer.
His dream job,
like any poor 10-year-old kid,
for which a football will always be worth all the prizes for excellence.
His father forced him to take up boxing.
Him,
He didn't want to be a boxer.
He wanted to be a footballer.
But his father forced him to take up boxing.
To avoid displeasing his father and to avoid getting beaten up,
because his father used to beat him and tie him up by his feet and everything,
He did it to please others.
SO,
if you wish
in the Cernon family,
It was boxing.
It was therefore with his father that Marcel learned boxing and fought his first professional fight at the age of 18.
in November 34.
And this time,
His match is completely overshadowed by the arrival in North Africa of the world bantamweight champion.
Panama Albran.
Eccentric star,
friend of Cocteau and of all Parisians
He came to Tunis to offer revenge to the man from whom he had taken the title.
the local boy,
Jung Perez.
Another darling of the Veldiv,
whose final battle would end tragically at Auschwitz.
Aware of his limitations as a manager and of his son's qualities,
Father Serdant chose long ago the person who would take care of Marcel.
Lucien Roupe,
a Frenchman from Morocco
a guy who has a garage and some young boxers whom he affectionately sponsors.
In 1937,
Marcel signs with this new father.
of which it becomes the most beautiful jewel.
Soon,
He no longer has a rival of his caliber in the Maghreb.
Then came the retirement of the great Georges Carpentier ten years earlier,
French boxing is orphaned.
And she gladly lends her rings to some twelve African birds,
having come to take refuge there in the shadow of the Roaring Twenties.
Even though times seem tougher in the late 1930s.
Following initial contact the previous year,
Rupp and his team arrived again in January 1938.
Marcel Hédan's early successes
three fights,
three chaos,
His manager quickly convinced Jeff Dixon,
the all-powerful boss of boxing in France,
to try to make Marcel the new darling of the Veldiv.
I dare you!
In May,
Dixon proposes that Rupp and his protégé face Gustave Hummery.
Tata said,
a terror of the ring
who exhausts his sparring partners.
Partners or adversaries,
they hit,
or even insult you.
until they take you down.
So hold on tight to Auntie,
romantic rendezvous at the Veldiv.
My father took a hit in the second round.
But he's out of it.
He comes back into the area,
he told Roup,
It really touched me.
He said,
Do you want us to give up?
Giving up is out of the question.
He said,
Leave me alone.
On the fifth,
at the four-fifth,
My father is recovering.
And he said to Roup,
That's it,
I've recovered.
He said,
Okay then,
Do your job.
Don't mess with Marcel,
nor call him a foreigner if you don't want to be a simpleton.
Terror now,
It's him.
the eye of the wild beast.
After the grey skies of Paris and the first attempts at elegance,
Heading to Milan for a bag.
In June 1939,
He crushes the Italian Turiello and easily becomes European Walter weight champion.
in front of a sea of ​​black shirts.
My father,
He should have been world champion at 22 if it hadn't been for the war.
He was already a European champion at 19.
20 years old,
Walter weights.
If there is no war,
He is the world champion in the Walter weight class.
September 1939.
While Hitler was undertaking the martyrdom of Poland,
before the plundering of Denmark and Norway,
France settles into the Phoney War.
Witness the inimitable Maurice Chevalier.
was in the industry,
the captain was in the insurance business,
and the second class had returned.
And all in excellent French.
excellent soldiers.
How do you expect a country to win a war after that?
Having entered Casablanca,
Marcel is mobilized in the navy.
He is responsible for carrying messages from the Admiralty to ships based in Arabia.
before being demobilized in June when the armistice came into effect.
How beautiful that summer of 1940 was in Morocco!
far from a Europe engulfed in fire and blood,
in the middle of the merry band of friends from the Roupe team.
Clearly,
the war,
It's definitely better in Gaza than anywhere else.
In Vichy,
For example,
where the new government of France was established.
In May 1941,
the small spa town,
eager to better establish her empire beyond the seas,
sends back to Africa.
Northern money,
a new d'Artagnan,
Jean Borotra,
former great musketeer of the glorious French tennis team of the 1920s.
The new commissioner for youth and sport is tasked with rallying the youth of the colonies and their champions,
in the name of the usual cheap values ​​of a Pétainist France that would like to be eternal.
All of this was, of course, topped off by the usual Olympic salute, which was as welcome as it was ambiguous.
I have just had the honor of delivering Marshal Pétain's message to you.
Upon my return to Vichy,
General,
I will report on my mission to the head of state.
I am sure I can tell him that North Africa is animated by a great faith and that it works with confidence in the shadow of the flag.
It was of course in the baggage of Vichy that Cerdan was forced to return to France.
Worship of the land demands it.
The sports department confined her to a farm near Antibes for the purposes of its propaganda.
Roub,
who did not want to leave his colt,
also lends itself to this little rural comedy which continues with a pleasant shadowboxing session in front of a beautiful French landscape.
What a waste of time for Cerdan!
European champion who dreams only of America and its champions.
For now,
He has to be content with repeating dodge and hook.
before engaging in a sparring session with a light flyweight.
Yet,
beyond the quig of the whole,
simply by observing the grace and natural elegance of her movements,
One can guess that it's a toothbrush holder.
adorned with all their teeth.
Finally,
Roup can get his Marcel back.
before Jean Desme,
the so-called filmmaker,
try to play Helen Riefenstahl.
And he is the God of the stadium,
To be continued in the next issue.
a number that Marcel, of course, doesn't even suspect.
Style is the man.
Buffon's words are true in boxing as elsewhere.
Look at Cerdan,
European champion,
young boy from France,
You have your soul.
your old-fashioned country.
But you will both meet tomorrow.
because you are the future of the one who hoped for you.
Cerdan deserved a lot from the regime.
But that doesn't mean they're going to let him go to America.
Instead, he is offered the chance to cross the demarcation line for a rematch against Gustave Hummery.
that everyone is waiting for.
And who seems to have bounced back.
Just enough to stand for 10 seconds.
K.O.
They didn't understand the time of this match.
Tatam's boxing career is over.
who will never step back into the ring.
300 francs for the best seats for 22 seconds of entertainment.
That's a high price to pay in these times of scarcity.
of unconsciousness.
and yellow canvases.
Soon to be gathered in this same Veldiv,
rid of his ring,
hence,
summer of 1942,
13,000 Jews will go to their deaths.
Occupied or unoccupied zone,
Rupp can no longer find an opponent.
Fortunately,
Switzerland is here.
neutral,
without qualms,
who sends him one of his own,
Ben Frely,
unknown to the battalion.
Of course,
The young girl will receive her stipend.
but quickly descends from his mountains and gets a beating.
is phenomenal.
Back to Veldiv.
European weightlifting champion Walter three years earlier against Turiello,
a man of Mussolini
Marcel is now facing a man from Franco's party, whom some see greeting him in a strange way.
The Spaniard José Ferrer.
This time,
The European title for average points is at stake.
My father avoided politics.
He took photos with the president and company.
But that's where it stopped.
He never took a stand for anyone.
For anyone,
He never got his hands dirty.
SO,
If you want to tell me something,
People tell him,
There,
You boxed Touriello.
You boxed Ferrer,
We have to box them.
Well,
They box them.
They are obliged to do it.
That's his job.
He did not stay.
He didn't drink champagne with the fascists.
He didn't drink the stuff.
He left immediately.
He didn't stay.
It seems that Marcel didn't like the Spaniard's sort of greeting either.
Always methodical,
He first observes his opponent,
but this time,
The gear ratio shifts very quickly.
Ferrer was knocked down with his first right hook.
Caramba!
Sharper than ever.
Overwhelming a referee who must regret not having gone to engineering school so he could count his constantly downed opponent quickly enough.
Marcel dispatches this championship in less than air with a weapon.
What's the point of continuing to count?
Those close to the Spaniard prefer to throw in the towel.
Out.
From this, to conclude that Cerdan,
by beating Ferrer,
has become a new figure of the French Resistance,
It's just a small step.
Mission accomplished.
The new European champion is going to take some time off at home in Morocco.
Barely a month later, Operation Torch took place.
The Allies landed more than 100,000 men in North Africa.
From November 8th,
The first units are taking a foothold on Algerian and Moroccan soil.
Less than three days later,
The armistice is signed and Morocco is liberated.
Serdant once again switches sides to the winning camp.
What determines the destiny of a champion?
Who is currently enjoying the joys of football again.
In January 1943,
Serdant marries the sister of one of his teammates,
Marinette Lopez.
Scandal.
Marcel is also a womanizer, and the jilted mistress makes sure everyone knows it.
A legitimate child is coming soon.
Marcel Junior.
And a hidden daughter.
In April,
He is mobilized again.
More sweat lost.
This time,
It was in the suitcase of the Allies that Cerdan reappeared in Rome in December 1944.
among the pompous remains of the Olympic Forum where the Americans organized the Inter-Allied Games.
As for Serdant,
He is practically the only foreign boxer involved.
He has already crushed two opponents in less than a round and is now preparing for his final, which will take place in a Brancaccio theater.
smoky and packed to the rafters.
His opponent,
American black sergeant Ralph Burnett,
two arms like paddles,
but his boxing style leaves much to be desired.
including a guard such as a carriage gate,
into which the hypercut of French rushes,
Magda.
Burnett gets back up, sealed.
Bisse repeated,
a second uppercut to the chin,
the thunderbolt,
this time for the account,
And much to the delight of the G.I.s, who were blown away by this Moroccan bomber,
the Moroccan bomber.
On the Champs-Élysées,
It's an American orchestra that's performing the Marseillaise.
at the Inter-Allied Cabaret,
sealing the idyll of Paris with its liberators.
As a new clientele crowds onto the dance floor to the rhythm of swing,
led by some new yet very familiar faces,
including Marlène Détriche,
who would not have wanted to see the Black Paris of the occupation for anything in the world.
The still rather paltry ratings for Bibop and Awakening of Victory cannot make us forget the general chaos of a country still at war.
where even ration tickets are useless,
because there is nothing left in the middle of the empty market halls, reduced to serving as sidewalks.
Paris was once again under a shroud in February 1945.
When Marcel returns, while the Allied offensive continues towards Germany,
where the Reich has not yet capitulated.
An unlikely period, or even in boxing,
Those of yesterday must give way to newcomers.
Including a certain Joe Longman,
the man with the dark glasses.
A former member of Leclerc's army who spotted Marcel.
Associate of the Famous Five,
new trendy box,
Longman is the greatest.
and his family also manages sports rights.
They are demanding exclusive rights to their fight from Roupe and his protégé.
What they accept in the face of this man's complacency, who opens the doors to another world for them and in whom Marcel sees for the first time a certain
Edith Piaf.
A champion always sets the tone.
The war ended and peace was signed five months ago,
It's good to see the light-colored uniforms of the British soldiers now.
Replacing the green-grey uniforms of the Wehrmacht to go to the Veldiv,
seeing Cerdan take on the Italians and Spaniards of yesterday
Tommy Davis,
a supposedly promising British man.
Even if he's not a true American yet.
Even though this young Welshman,
primary boxing,
larger and heavier,
not to say Marcel, who is rather plump,
he struggles to lift his feet from the ground he is finally getting to know.
after just 2 minutes and 30 seconds of fighting.
Before Cerdan,
true to himself,
doesn't help him get up,
That's also why the public loves it.
So much haze,
of brilliance in the ring,
So much simplicity and kindness in life.
Now all of France is demanding its own tank top.
The reconstruction effort, which began in 1945 with a focus on coal,
particularly in the Forès region.
They are thousands of metalworkers and coal miners converging en masse towards a square of light.
The one in the Saint-Etienne sports hall.
Ousserdan,
for his last fight of the year,
is opposed to Victor Butin,
heavy friend,
towards the end of his career,
the unique feature of sitting down during the rounds.
Sometimes on the ground,
sometimes swaying by the ropes,
It's the ring before ending up on his knees for good.
Already,
1946,
And still no Americans in sight.
Failing that,
to create a sensation with a match of the century, French-style, at the Parc des Princes.
where nearly 40,000 spectators are expected,
This is unprecedented for a boxing match.
Cerdan's entourage,
including Longman,
the man with the dark glasses,
has set its sights high for this fight that all of France is waiting for.
who must oppose Cerdan,
the magnificent,
to Bob the Chestnut.
Alias
Robert Charon,
a good boxer who plays the heartthrob when he's not playing the bad guy.
From the Famous Five,
He only loves his chickens.
who takes him to train with him a short walk away in Montmartre,
playing the heartthrob and getting into orbit before concluding somewhere other than in a boxing ring.
Quite the opposite of Lucien Roupe's well-behaved child,
came to practice with the ladybug and that Charon,
As the times dictated,
call the bico.
Just to stir things up.
To the sandbag,
The serdent is moving less quickly than usual.
Roupe has just been kidnapped.
to retrieve him after an extended stay at his home in Morocco.
It's true that Marcel,
gifted boxer,
is not a training fanatic.
It doesn't matter,
The press is complicit, using sympathetic images.
Above all,
not to scratch the idol.
Visibly,
that works.
From the morning,
Everyone is present.
The good thing about Marcel,
That's because its audience ranges from the gutter crowd in the upper stands to the true sportsman.
This is what the team is already reading.
Passing by the elite that we try in vain to glimpse over there.
In the middle of the lawn,
on the ring chairs.
Reggiani.
Carpentier.
37,000 people waiting for nightfall.
Fights including the 3-minute replay.
The French champion,
It is
Cerdan,
Jerome,
Charon.
Even from behind
the boastful, swaggering pest.
While Cerdan begins the...
The fight is still serious.
Turned,
observed,
gauge.
Charon, who is wary of maintaining his rights at a distance.
Cerdan, who is in average form, knows he has to act quickly.
Just a moment,
His opponent forgets his good intentions and retaliates instead of backing down.
A lightning-fast left hook.
And Charon already on the ground.
Get up slowly to recover better.
An old secret that the other one knows well.
Marcel immediately sought to take advantage of his position.
Let's use the battering rams to better demolish them.
But even under a hail of chestnuts,
Bob the Chestnut is a tough nut to crack.
Serdant may well search for the opening,
But Charon,
like an old ring kingpin,
He also embraced something other than his grandpas.
And with each stroke of the gong,
He wiggles,
Glad to still be standing.
Twelfth round.
Only three minutes left to get rid of Robert the Devil,
of his cunning.
of his tricks and his underwear effects.
Finally,
another left hook that sends him to the mat again.
But once again,
Charon comes out of his box.
To be defeated by Serdant,
Yes,
but standing,
even if it meant sticking to the very end like a limpet to the one he had called a "bico".
At the final gong,
The two fake enemies congratulate each other.
Defeated but applauded,
Bob Lachatel,
his face like a watermelon
can boast of having held
12 rounds.
As for Cerdan,
amidst flashing cameras and the whistles of a disappointed audience,
He remains the French champion.
A nice scholarship at stake and still unscathed despite his poor form.
Do you know what my father used to say?
When I was 20 years old and I got punched,
I was thinking,
shit,
that bastard,
I'm going to give him a whack.
You'll see.
And at 30,
when I get hit,
I was telling him,
Marcel,
It hurts.
Raise your hands.
Do you see the difference?
20 years old and 30 years old.
On the evening of the match against Charon,
and to the sound of Michel Hémer's jazz orchestra,
They are all in the Famous Five.
ladies,
Jacqueline Longman in the lead,
hoping to see the crash sit beside them.
It's true that she's pleasant for the former poor grandchild of Casa,
this revenge taken against misery,
and that it is good now,
all this luxury,
to win by punching.
Even if, through repeated hitting,
These are proving to be increasingly fragile,
like pearls.
Clearly,
It was time we also celebrated this first contract.
hooks across the Atlantic.
and which finally opens the doors of America to him,
kingdom of boxing.
November 19th, morning,
New York shrouded in fog, and finally the reward for ten years of work.
of effort and sacrifice.
At Madison Square Garden,
temple of New York boxing,
He meets on the same day,
Mike Jacobs,
Lord of boxing in the USA.
next to whom Marcel soon finds himself sitting.
Stay here for a long time.
I have several battles for you.
Lucien and Joe,
Of course,
approve.
That's it,
It's over.
More than a formality,
the visit to the legendary square hall where all the champions of the century once paraded.
Finally,
The New York by Night tour can begin.
That's also what makes a champion like Serdant,
someone from here who,
before everyone else,
allows us to see each other there.
And to dream that one day, perhaps,
here,
it should be like over there.
After the glitz of the neon lights,
the dilapidated state of the training facilities.
The one where Georgie Abrams trains,
champion of furnished rooms,
classified nevertheless
5th highest average score in the world.
Which is no small thing.
The always suitable group chose the Catholic School Young Organization.
An amateur venue where Serdant seems to be in good form in front of his staff on Sunday.
An interview with the champion is a must.
although he still struggles to read the quick reference guide installed under the camera.
I am very happy to be in America.
because it's a very beautiful country.
I thank the Americans very much for the friendly way they received me.
I hope to put on a good fight.
to please them very much,
to try and come and talk,
if possible,
the world championship.
The day after,
Abraham will smile less, and Serdant,
victorious,
will be able to say
“My head swelled up,
"But it's because of the Nyons."
Early 1947,
Another Frenchman has returned.
The priceless man in the boater hat.
Hello Mr. Lave,
Here I am back in New York after an absence of 14 years.
I came back here to do my job as a traveler with French sympathies.
I will do everything I can to show the French side of my songs to the American public.
I also hope it's redant.
will perhaps bring the world championship title back to France.
Finally,
We are trying to do good work for the country.
After having to publicly justify his attitude to the Anglo-Saxon press at the end of the war,
let's say,
a little soft,
during the conflict,
The inimitable Momo is back on the American market and wouldn't miss the opportunity to redeem himself by appearing alongside the new French darling.
But let's get down to business.
For his second fight in the USA,
The Moroccan bomber is scheduled to meet a promising young American pilot.
He took on Harold Green, 22 years old.
He was the future world champion.
He ruined the career.
He gave up boxing after that.
He gave it to her
10 fights.
He himself said,
I haven't done 10 fights.
I've competed in 10 world championships.
All the teams I've encountered,
They were potential world champions.
The very young kid from Brooklyn,
Harold Green...
had signed up for the fight with a smile on his face.
It's the same straight line from Marcel that will strike him down.
The execution lasted two rounds.
After the sweat of the Madison,
Cerdan,
back in Paris,
dons its finery,
although black,
to attend the 1947 ball of the little white beds,
of which he is one of the star guests.
That evening,
Edith Piaf also performed at this obligatory post-war gala,
in front of all those who consider themselves the cream of the crop,
buying their clear conscience with charity tickets.
Curtain.
October 47.
Piaf,
with the companions,
her lover Jean-Louis Jobert in particular,
embarks on his first tour in North America.
My father and Edith met in 1946.
It didn't go well, by the way.
They met in Paris.
They didn't have much contact, the two of them.
And my father had to box in New York.
And they called each other.
I don't know if it was him or her who called.
I don't know.
I think it's more likely that she called him.
They met and then went to dinner together.
After,
They ended up in bed.
That,
I don't know.
Of course they end up in bed and even spend long periods of time in this New York that they are discovering together.
Piaf has a revelation for this type of person.
as she says,
whose strength is matched only by its simplicity and integrity.
He is touched by the little girl who also comes from there in part.
with his Kabyle grandmother,
like him, starting from nothing to reach the firmament.
A new mistress who also opens the doors to another world for him.
Piaf and he stayed together for a few more days.
Before Marcel returns,
While Edith, ever generous, consoles Jaubert, who clings on, and especially one of those handsome guys she adores,
the Hollywood star,
John Garfield.
New Year 1948,
the first battles in Paris.
It was Longman who convinced Marcel to accept this match of false brilliance against an Italian pal.
European title at stake.
just to make the cash register ring in front of an opponent who kneels before he's even asked.
First lockdown,
And the comedy begins again.
approved by Edith who also encourages him to reap the rewards of his punches.
February 1948,
a new beginning in the USA.
To meet the daring Laver Roach,
young Texan, 23 years old.
Best hope for average points that serves in the mine 7 rounds of the rank.
Before executing it on the 8th attempt.
Why are they giving my father 10 fights before he can box the world champion?
Because we don't want him to be world champion,
We don't want him to take the title.
We know he's going to take the title.
So we give him people who are capable of beating him.
They give him people who are capable of beating him.
And unfortunately for them,
My father was stronger than them.
He hit them all.
For what ?
You don't know how my father killed him 7 or 8 times in a boxing match?
Did they die above the battle?
7 or 8,
You don't know that?
Go find the Boxing Federation,
Tell that to the number of people Marcel Sartre killed.
And you believe that at Venroche,
than to Radic,
after my father,
Will he be able to box?
He no longer boxes.
Edith witnessed the massacre.
Marcel shares with the little girl.
as he likes to call it,
a success that America now seems to offer to the one who agreed to translate life into pink.
By U2
Dangerous, darling.
What a terrific song!
That's also what boxing and Serdant are about.
Men who die,
Two experts in their field who fall in love for a moment, and the public,
who dream of everything, and especially of what a complicit press is keen to hide from them.
She goes downstairs first, and he follows.
without even realizing it,
before pretending to find her.
It was wonderful that little Pierre saw you.
He said it well.
The bouquet for another,
while Marcel no longer knows whether he should greet or take by the shoulders the one he has just held in his arms every night.
It's difficult to reconcile the songs of Toto and his band with Edith's music theory lessons.
For Marcel,
came to Veldiv,
to kick off its six days,
He is so much more comfortable among his own people.
While the rounds unfold in an atmosphere of merguez sausages,
where a bike ride will more surely remind you of Morocco.
Than a 78 rpm microgroove record.
It is a well-fed and determined Servant who appears on May 23rd at the Ezel stadium in Brussels for a European championship against the young Belgian Delanois, who is facing Marcel, to whom the group...
Serine,
for weeks,
Love is ruining your legs.
It seems the Belgian Tarzan believes in his chances.
although he practices a rather crude style of boxing,
still known as a lumberjack and exposing himself to Marcel's counter.
who nevertheless takes it in stride without batting an eye,
before launching another attack.
Less dazzling than usual,
Marcel struggles to hit an opponent who can barely shake him.
Fifteenth and final round.
The fight is already behind him.
Serdant must finish the job and throws all his strength into the battle.
For a moment,
The shadow of the true Servant looms over the ring.
chaining together series of body shots in front of a Tarzan who dodges and now engages reverse gear.
It was all in vain at the end of the round; the other man was still standing, but Cerdan was confident. Yet it was his young opponent's arm that the referee, the sole judge, raised, declaring him the winner, while over there in his corner, Marcel Abassourdi threw himself to the ground in despair.
He dreamed of a world championship, but he's no longer even the European champion, stripped of his crown by a guy nobody believed in.
You know, Delannoy,
What did he do?
Delannoy,
He boxed my father twice.
Unfortunately for the Belgians.
They reported my father beaten.
First 15 rounds.
Yes,
He is not trained.
the referee...
They have a second fight.
second fight,
15 rounds.
That makes 30 rounds.
You know how it ended,
Delannoy?
He was walking down the street.
When a bus passed by,
the bus gang,
he was taking precautions,
He believed that the fight was beginning.
That's how you end up when you box against such a bastard.
If we're not dead,
We finish at the quarter mark.
Fortunately,
Roub,
careful,
had negotiated a possible rematch within two months.
This time,
Marcel takes this seriously.
With my friend Toto Grassin,
former cycling champion and his usual sparring partners,
Marcel resurfaces.
Everyone was there.
So, however,
Mr.
Roub included,
with them,
Jogging seems less boring.
To oxygenate,
We play at being goats on the rocks in the Rambouillet forest,
before jumping on a ball that has never held any secrets for this boxer,
who has a ball in his head.
Cherry cake
Marinette, the woman of good times and bad, and Junior are here.
Public rehabilitation operation required
Indeed,
Marcel is going to need everyone behind him
Cerdan is about to take a big gamble.
Not so much against Delannoy, whom he will eventually overcome, but against a much more formidable opponent.
Cerdan has just been named challenger to the new world champion
Tony Zell, thank you.
The Man of Steel,
who has finally overcome his eternal rival,
Rocky Graziano,
during a beautiful display of dentology that surpassed their first match in intensity.
And revenge.
Watching these two gladiators kill each other in the ring.
No wonder America never wanted to give Cerdan a chance.
Until these two blood-spilling, money-making machines had definitively settled their score.
It is this statue of liberty made of tempered steel that awaits Marcel.
August 25th,
This time is the right one.
The new Constellation sleeper carrying Cerdan and his staff finally emerges from the ocean night.
Mid-afternoon,
The plane finally flies over Manhattan.
Not a moment too soon, considering how long we've been waiting for them down here.
Because in America,
One match already.
Indeed,
It's at stake.
But it also sells.
And the pseudo-signing session at Gallagher's restaurant is a classic.
Even though it was a long time ago, of course,
that the contracts are locked up.
I would like to thank Tony Zal for giving me this chance to compete in the world championship.
And if I win,
I hope to be a great champion like him.
Thank you Marcel.
That's enough for me.
But beyond the expected statements, and with these two brave fellows about to clash,
There are essentially two worlds.
The old and the new, illuminating and speaking to each other.
At the Evans Hotel,
near New York,
Serdant refines its form and displays the name of its host,
that we don't yet call a sponsor.
Having his ever-wonderful footwork,
We thought that Edith was arriving in her turn,
but always hidden
had to put on his chastity belt for once in order to allow him to split the world champion's belt.
Carpentier is here too.
still popular since his fight of the century here against Jake Dempsey.
Even Pierre de Gaulle,
brother of the man of June 18th,
will come to encourage him,
while it is now up to Marcel to launch his appeal of September 21st.
My dear friends,
The long-awaited day has finally arrived.
Needless to say, I am overjoyed.
To think that I'm going to discuss the leader of one of the world's leaders.
6000 kilometers away,
The streets empty and an entire country holds its breath.
Hello,
well Grenèche,
We hear you perfectly.
And here is the broadcast of the Marseillaise.
We are just seconds away from the start of the match.
Of course,
The cameras here have no god but the one nicknamed the man of steel.
Tony Zell,
reigning champion,
but also an exemplary soldier during the war and an exemplary father.
Brief,
A man just the way America likes them.
From the very start of the match,
We use it well for leg exercises.
Right into the game.
LEFT,
RIGHT,
series about Marcel's body.
The man of steel is shaken like a plum tree.
First round.
Zell,
old fox of the ring,
already hinders his opponent.
The terrible ordeal against Rocky,
less than three months earlier,
must have left traces.
Not to mention the new stigmas.
While Serdant,
well online,
behind the rampart of his guard,
he darts his dark, serious gaze.
Every time the world champion touches the ball,
He in turn receives his dose of oats.
There remains the psychological weapon of a lingering look.
It continues.
A pathetic Marcel continues his undermining work.
of moral and physical destruction
while Zell still feels the need to take a break.
Always lucid,
Serdant searches for and finds the opening every time.
As for Zell,
Let's move on.
In this little game,
Marcel quickly becomes
The Terrific Frenchie,
not disdaining hand-to-hand combat either.
And despite a few setbacks,
Zell is now nothing more than a drifter.
Man of steel turned into modeling clay,
kneaded by fists,
even the arms of toothbrush holders.
When it's not the ropes of the ring biting his back.
At the sound of the gong,
Zell, trailing in the score, rushes forward.
To die better,
What's the point?
He no longer even has the strength to raise his guard.
into which Marcel's left hook sinks.
As the hour of agony strikes and at the queen's feet is said, "Farewell only to the executioner,"
who feels he is going to win,
and is waiting to be able to carry the stockades.
I will go,
I will never go.
Zell,
Stranded in the dark night of Jersey City,
does not show up for the call of the twelfth round.
And without his crown, Marcel Cerdan
the first post-war hero of a new France.
In France,
It's madness everywhere.
It was also the entire country that Marcel raised to the level of its great American ally.
during a match that had become like a wedding ring,
uniting the two shores of the Atlantic.
And for the time being,
France and its people will have to wait.
Enjoy,
Yes,
despite the marks,
Enjoy Edith's company while you can and celebrate this wonderful title with her between official appearances.
privacy and going out in the evening
particularly at Versailles
of which the little lady in black armor is now the queen.
They were both coming from...
From below,
that is to say, not poor,
but almost,
He was coming out of his stocking.
And suddenly,
They are both at the top of a poster.
It's dizzying.
And then suddenly,
these two,
they said to themselves,
It's unimaginable.
We have everyone on the other side now.
It's fabulous.
Early October,
Cerdan is finally reunited with his beloved Casa.
showing off his new belt in front of all those who knew him,
poor children from a working-class neighborhood.
That's probably why he's laughing so simply and relaxed like never before.
Less than a week later,
Paris receives him as a true war hero.
This November 13th,
It sits enthroned amidst numerous French athletes.
Among them,
the great Micheline Ostermeier.
Double Olympic champion in athletics in London,
the same year.
Moreover, she is a great concert pianist.
the quintessence of what is most beautiful in sport,
the alliance of power and art,
eclipsed by all the serdents in the world,
those who, without even knowing it,
coincide with their time.
When night falls, he too rekindles the flame.
to the right of General Giraud,
the very same one whom the Americans had chosen during the war to overshadow De Gaulle,
whom he distrusted.
While Cerdan now stood amidst the flags of Free France,
gains a new rank chosen by history.
And too bad for all those who arrived too late.
In France,
since the end of the war,
There are a few of them scouring the rings and knocking on the door behind Serdent.
In particular, a certain Robert Villemin,
a strong steer,
who boxes like he unloads his sacks of potatoes and who hits like a devil.
Or, to put it another way,
Laurent Dautuil,
said the Tarzan of Buzynval,
long at work.
But don't touch Marcel!
because if boxing is a journey of initiation,
His science is also the science of money.
There's no question of burning out a champion like Serdant before he's given his all.
and to make him take the slightest risk against some ambitious young people.
All of this will have to wait.
as he himself waited for America.
End of year 48,
and Junior, already a fighter.
while the camera pulls back to vaguely reveal the Moroccan fir tree.
Christmas.
Perfect time to shoot a short, educational film.
supposed to set the record straight.
Isn't life beautiful among the Cerdans?
Where Mr. and Mrs. play the parents so well,
even if the lady's kisses,
if it's done properly
seem a bit forced.
Mom,
dad.
And then of course the good one.
as it should be.
The gentleman is arriving.
It's true, these new porcelain teeth are stunning.
Probably advised by Piaf, who reinforced his desire to make films.
And French studios are seeing new faces arrive.
Marcel Serdant,
for whom the makeup artist succeeds the caregiver,
has passed,
Oh, not for long.
From the ring to the studio.
Spine studio.
The Man with Clay Hands by Léon Matto.
A beautiful title.
but also an avet.
Supposed to recount the life of Marcel.
Piaf turned pale when she heard the director's name.
Too late.
It doesn't matter what the bottle is,
provided that the intoxication is such,
and above all, no one to get in the way of things.
The prudish Mr. Roub.
He's already receiving a quarter of his earnings.
that he not interfere in the rest.
Breakup.
A murky story about money was used as a pretext.
Result,
There were ten years of companionship with a guy who was a bit like a father to me.
And all the space is given to Joe Longman.
He's been aiming for that position for a long time.
Former music impresario close to Piaf,
this new nurse,
protects from being set aside,
doesn't know much about the noble art.
nor of his discipline and even less of the dirty tricks which sometimes also occur outside the ring.
In May 1949,
Jim Norris succeeds Mike Jacobs,
at the head of the powerful International Boxing Club.
A leader who is leaving,
Another one is coming.
What's surprising, except that the new one is directly linked to the mafia.
Against all expectations, but as a logical consequence of the case,
A certain Jack Lamotta has been designated by the new American boxing authorities as the Frenchman's challenger.
even though he was far down on the list of contenders.
That makes sense, though.
Lamotta, known as the Bronx bull, had voluntarily thrown 18 months earlier in front of an opponent to please a staff of mafia bettors.
In exchange for which,
He had been promised that one day he would be able to compete for the title.
And on this day...
had now arrived.
Jack Latriche is a real beast.
accustomed to hitting his opponent like a madman, when he's not hitting his wife-in-law.
It is this not-so-clean boxer that Serdant will now have to face.
New signing session
more discreet than with Tony Zell,
The Bronx bull cannot be exposed too much.
Cerdan hesitates.
Boxing or film contract?
Let's go with this match between two films.
against this guy who probably can't read,
but who signs his initials like a true businessman.
It's in Detroit itself,
the meeting place where Marcel continues his preparations.
At the pace of a sandbag,
Of course,
but also letters that Edith Piaf sent him from France.
Two weeks before the fight,
she wrote
I have only one desire,
it's about resembling you
To have your simplicity and your moral grandeur
For happiness,
trust me
I'll do anything for you
I'll use everything for you
I will gather everything for you
I will go with you to the heaven of love
Where I can love you the way I want to
Everything is there.
In any case,
the lyrics of the hymn to love,
that she is composing at the same time.
A song that will soon be a worldwide hit.
while his sparring also revolves around the champion,
while moving forward like a Jack LaMotta,
without being Jack Lamotta.
Deadly illusion.
June 16, 1949
Detroit,
Rain is threatening.
So the Challenger is the first to enter the arena ahead of schedule.
In her ever-present leopard-print outfit,
The Bronx bull seems determined to win this title.
that has been waved under his nose for a while.
Yet,
We can't get enough of this bad boy.
Only a small amateur camera was present that day.
It also allows us to admire the lovely Vicky.
This time...
The bull, which usually charges so early in the enclosure, cannot find a way in.
facing a world champion who is well in line.
And the recovery is not yet complete.
that some can already feel the hot breath of the unleashed beast.
Initially closed like an oyster,
It reveals itself under a hail of taste.
retreating,
and then trying to cling to a wild animal that throws him to the ground like a common bundle of dirty laundry.
The beast is not so much aiming for its opponent's head.
The target is too small.
She prefers to hit people directly.
where the pile driver of its wide hooks can break you in two and mince your liver.
While Marcel,
still very much online
despite the turbulence,
waits for his moment and to be able to unleash one of his devastating counter-attacks.
That's strange, all the same.
This world champion who only uses one arm.
The law remains the same.
While his other weapon,
the left,
remains mysteriously stuck to the body.
La mota understood.
His injured opponent became one-armed.
confident.
Now it is he who waits and seeks the fatal blow.
While Marcel continues to move forward with the energy of despair,
taking the hit and ready to die rather than surrender.
We had never seen Marcel used as a sandbag before.
A bull turned bullfighter
advancing with his arms dangling, so certain was he of the kill.
Marcel has been dying for 20 minutes.
The bull needs to breathe, so now he's playing cat and mouse.
World champion for barely 9 months,
and Marcel became a shadow of his former self.
Left to be exploited by a hateful man,
A sad end to the finals.
interrupted by the bell at the end of the ninth round.
This time,
It is Marcel's turn to not answer the call for the next round.
as she had done,
nine months earlier,
as Jack Lamotta might do one day.
Boxing is like a limpet that never lets go of its prey.
whether in the shadow of a ring or in the glare of victory.
Even if a son wouldn't believe it.
My father,
He is preparing for his fight against Jacques Lamotta.
He's in the locker room.
He's in the locker room and we're moving the fight forward by half an hour.
We catch him cold and he enters the ring cold.
He slips.
He was never knocked out.
He never...
He slipped and fell.
And he puts his shoulder down.
Not the right shoulder, unfortunately.
the left shoulder.
The shoulder where there is...
where we protect ourselves and where he can strike.
The right wing,
He has it like that,
the blows,
You take it.
August 49.
New York.
The rematch was finally scheduled for the end of September.
Five weeks to prepare.
Especially before the final stretch.
to spend a little more quality time with Edith,
in the New York apartment.
Even though Piaf,
always hidden from the cameras,
appears absent.
Everyone ends up in Manhattan.
Loulou Barrier,
the little girl's manager.
The sycophantic longman behind his dark glasses,
Paul Janser,
the close friend, confidant
In his own way, a more Hollywood-esque servant than ever before,
on which and under which Piaf finally handed over notes and handcuffs.
Let's not forget the ultimate reason for this trip,
the match against that old rogue from La Mota.
who submits without any problem to the pre-fight medical examination,
mandatory in the USA.
In any case,
for what an oath is worth,
Was it Hippocratic?
My father was in New York for the rematch and Graziano,
OK Graziano,
He went to see my father at training.
Training,
He went to work for Jacques Lamotta.
He said Jacques,
He is Italian.
two Italians,
Graziano and Lamotta.
He said Jacques,
Don't take it.
He's going to kill you.
Message received loud and clear, or real injury.
In any case,
The Bronx bull withdraws four days before the fight.
preferring to play the lamb with his son rather than the tough guy with Marcel.
Eighth return to the eternal constellation that allows us to see America so well.
You can find everything down there,
except for Morocco.
And you can find everything at the little one's place.
except for one family and their relatives.
This time,
despite Edith's pleas,
who always wants more,
Marcel flies to France.
When he lands at Orly,
The man who always laughed no longer smiles.
As for his comments about the motorcyclist's evasive maneuver,
They are surely appropriate for the circumstances.
Quickly,
Morocco.
Find Marinette,
the children,
his relatives,
In short, the family, who are not afraid to speak their minds about this Mediterranean double,
Spanish by origin and Moroccan by adoption.
Three sons now,
and their friends,
not to mention his beloved farm in Sidi Marouf and his pigs which amuse him.
It's true that it still looks dilapidated with all its hectares lying fallow.
But everything remains to be done since it is here,
in Morocco,
that he wants to live,
and also over there,
in the city,
where his brewery awaits him,
and the new house whose foundation stone he has just laid.
Gaza,
towards which he is now heading,
in this October rain.
And still these two worlds,
Anne,
Plane,
to find his way back to the city where all his memories are,
and where nothing seems to have really changed since the 1920s.
Except perhaps for a baseball cap replacing a shaved head and the colors of a short film shot with friends,
to which Marcel serves as driver and guide.
October 26,
Paris,
D-2.
For the past few days,
Marcel knows that the rematch against Mota has been set for December 2nd.
Tomorrow,
He has to leave for the USA.
Always helpful,
He nevertheless agreed to participate in an exhibition match in Troyes.
to please a friend.
even if it means having to return to Paris in the middle of the night.
My father returns to Paris in the evening.
In the car,
There are four of them.
And all of a sudden,
One of them said to my father,
My father was in the process of fussing,
He told my father,
Why are you leaving now?
You have time to leave.
So, my father,
he said,
Turn on the radio.
He turns on the radio and it's Pierre Fkishon.
He said,
Well, that's why I'm leaving.
for her,
to join her.
Because she had written,
she had told him,
There,
I have a few days of vacation.
instead of taking your boat,
come,
That way we can spend a few days together before your world championship.
So,
It was simple.
October 27,
D-1.
Marcel leaves Langman's apartment.
At Orly,
He poses one last time with Ginette Neveu.
young virtuoso violinist.
She hands him her Stradivarius.
musical instrument par excellence.
Although Edith knew nothing about boxing,
On the other hand...
As for life and its symbols,
It is 2:55 AM
GMT, this 28th of October 1949,
when Cerdan's plane stopped responding,
and will never again respond to the control tower of the Azores island.
On the ground,
an inextricable charnel house
and 48 corpses.
Marcel's watch was identified thanks to one of the three watches that this champion of all worlds always wore.
each at their respective Paris time,
New York and Casablanca.
When the Liberator brings Marcel's body home,
They are here.
his brothers.
They too were former boxers.
at the head of the procession.
And then there are the women,
Of course,
but as it should be, behind.
All knocked out.
Facing this champion who was never considered out.
Except by fate.
Along the route,
70,000 people watched him cross these cities one last time.
escorted by two young champions carrying relics of years born barely 33 years old.
To the sound of the church bells of Our Lady of Lourdes,
and above the Msyk cemetery,
two names resonating in European and Arabic languages.
like many of those present that day,
not to mention a certain Don Quixote from the Rignes area,
returned to greet his former protégé and friend,
before he was buried in his Moroccan soil.
At Paris-Au-Vel-Divre,
Six former world champions have left one place empty among them.
that of their former companions.
He was also greeted by tens of thousands of people in stadiums across France.
honoring the memory of a deceased champion who will not see this new world of the 1950s,
to which he had helped to give its full impetus.
People are struck by death.
We're counting down,
that's because of Romeo and Juliet,
They join Piaf and they die.
That,
It always remains etched in someone's mind.
In 1960,
Piaf is 45 years old and remembers.
Whose?
She's had so many men,
while he,
Cerdan,
dissolved underground.
But deep down,
never mind.
It is enough to know that a great champion never belongs to himself body and soul.
So many people want to have it and see it.
Where he himself could never be.
That is what makes it both ridiculous and glorious.
Otherwise,
It's like the son who would have aged him and never grown up.
Marcel Cerdan,
a French legend.
1,
2,
3,